[Music]
[Applause]
the most common question i receive is
how often should i train the glutes i
addressed that in yesterday's video
in today's video i'm going to address
the second most common question that i
receive
and that pertains to gluten balances you
know people write me
how do i fix a gluten balance so the
first thing i want to say about gluten
balance is that you should be a little
bit imbalanced nobody's perfectly
symmetrical
you know if you talk about something
people become paranoid about it this
happens with butt wink and a squat
knee valgus anterior pelvic tilt you
mentioned these things to people and all
of a sudden they become so paranoid and
while
a lot of those things is bad a little
bit is fine you don't need to worry
about it you know it's normal for
most people say you're right-handed
right-footed
you'll kick your whole life with your
right foot so you plant off your left
leg kick with your right leg so your
left hip extensor tends to be a little
bit stronger
and your right hip flexor tends to be a
little bit stronger so it's normal to
have an imbalance of like 10
in strength and in terms of size look at
bodybuilders they're not perfectly
symmetrical the left
bicep might be a little bit bigger than
the right bicep you'll see it with the
pecs
delts lats you see it with glutes you
know a 10
difference is nothing to be concerned
about that's normal and think about it
it's functional too
should professional baseball players be
like wait i swung the bat 30 times
you know on my on my right side i should
30 times on my left side
no they shouldn't should boxers take the
opposite stance
and practice striking no they shouldn't
the same goes with golfers and tennis
players etc you're gonna have a
preferred side and that's functional you
want to be more coordinated
more skillful stronger and more powerful
off one side because it's advantageous
to do so
think about it it makes you more
functional if you wasted time always
trying to be symmetric you wouldn't get
as good
on the one side i get a lot of people
coming to me concerned about their
glute imbalance i can remember this one
guy he was
you know very paranoid and he swore he
had a glute imbalance you know i i gave
him a battery of tests for like 20
minutes and then i
i said the guy said listen through every
test that i know of
you came up symmetrical you know i had
you do glute bridges
and i palpated they feel the same size
they're the same density they contract
to the same degree of hardness
you know i had him do goblet squats he
didn't shift to one side
he was very symmetrical with his
bilateral movement patterns like squats
and hinges
and thrusts and bridges and he was the
same strength on single leg exercises
like
lunges bulgarian split squats he didn't
have a big strength discrepancy
so if it looks symmetrical it feels
symmetrical
and it performs symmetrical there's not
a problem
but he swore he could feel a difference
and i'm sure he could
you know it's normal to get a better
mind muscle connection on one side than
the other but for the glutes people get
really paranoid you know i've never had
anyone come to me and be like
i have a bicep imbalance i have a tricep
imbalance i have a delt imbalance
i have a trap imbalance i have a latin
balance i have an erector imbalance
i have a hamstring imbalance i have a
quad imbalance i have a calvin bounce i
have an ab imbalance it's always just
the glutes and it's because people care
about glutes so much now
on the flip side i have trained a couple
of clients with
severe glute imbalances one of them won
the miss bikini olympia she was very
crafty at posing
to hide her imbalance but one client in
particular she had a
really big imbalance and it was crazy
because
one glute was like over twice the size
of the other
and then the opposite erector was over
twice the size of the other
so she had this erector and this glute
that was crazy muscular and these
uh this diagonal pair that was atrophied
now i'll get to the strategy i developed
for her in a minute but before i do that
let me go through the solutions that
i've come up with as a trainer
over the years so the first method i
came up with probably ten years ago
was what i call the two to one method
and with this method you just perform
twice the amount of volume for the
weaker glute than you do for the
stronger glute and
theoretically the extra volume would
help you converge over time you know you
would have this discrepancy
and then over time they would converge
and you would iron out that imbalance
you shouldn't strive for perfectly equal
just within 10
or so you want to bridge the gap a
little bit sometimes so while the 2 1
method
worked decently well i don't think it's
aggressive enough so i no longer do it
so the next method i came up with and
this is what i wrote about in glute lab
was the ankle weight
single leg reverse hyper method and
basically you just do
one legged reverse hypers slap an ankle
weight on and do them like
three to five times a week do them
before the workout while you're fresh
for like three sets and what's nice
about this is you're doing it first
thing in the workout you're not fatigued
you're given a good strengthening
stimulus several times a week and that
should make a difference over time but
then you just do your normal workout
and in theory things would even out over
time now the two to one method and the
ankle weight single leg reverse hyper
method
we're successful i got a lot of emails
over there saying thank you very much
you know i stumbled across your article
and it helped me fix my imbalance but
with some people
it's just not enough you need something
more aggressive so with the client i
mentioned earlier with the
craziest imbalance i've ever seen this
led me to develop another method
and this is the single leg day method so
with her i'd have her come three days a
week
she'd do one bilateral day per week and
two unilateral days per week but on the
unilateral day
she didn't train the stronger side she
just trained the weaker side so in her
case i believe it was her right glute
that was a lot bigger
i would just do a left legged day now
let's talk about exercise selection
what exercise are best for helping fix
the imbalance automatically i'm going to
exclude knee dominant glute movements
like bulgarian split squats step ups
lunges single leg box squats and pistols
and skater squats why because yes they
work the glute but they also work the
quad a lot if you do a ton of these then
you're going to develop a quad imbalance
the
the quad on the weaker glute on the side
of the weaker glute
is going to get stronger than the other
side and you're not going to be
in symmetry i'm also going to exclude
single leg straight leg hip extension
movements like the single legged rdl
the single leg 45 degree hyper because
same thing here with the hamstring the
hamming on the weaker glute side
will now get stronger than the other
side and again you won't be in symmetry
so where does that leave us well my
favorite
is obviously the ankle weight single leg
reverse hyper
but i also love the cable kickback with
single hypnosis you do feel the quad and
the hamstring a little bit
more than i'd like you can do them with
body weight with a dumbbell
with a smith machine with a land mine so
lots of ways to do single leg reverse
hypers
also in terms of abduction i like the
extra range sideline hip abduction
and finally there's a cool thing i do
with my glute loops and basically i have
the client put the glute loop right
above the knees
they stand against a wall or hold on to
like a
like a squat rack or something and they
basically do a three-way kickback
meaning
kick straight back kick back at a 45
degree angle
kick to the side so you're basically
doing a mixture of hip extension hip
abduction then abduction so you'll
strengthen the whole entire glute now
how do you know if you have a glute
imbalance if you have a glute imbalance
that's going to manifest itself with
muscle growth
you'll see it one glute will be markedly
bigger than the other now one glute
might be significantly stronger than the
other
and you'll know this because there'll be
certain exercises like single leg hip
thrusts
where you're just way weaker on the one
side compared to the other and finally
if you feel one glute working way more
than the other you might want to devote
some extra attention to that side that
doesn't activate as well that alone is
not enough to warrant
extreme measures like having a single
leg day as i explained before
so in conclusion there's a lot of people
that are borderline paranoid about
having a gluten balance
it's normal it's functional you're gonna
have one glute that's a little bit
stronger than the other just based on
your everyday life and especially if you
play sports
sometimes you might not understand why
there's this imbalance it could be
related to some
other factor like you know an injury
that
never got rehabbed properly and it could
be some type of anatomical
anomaly you know you see this crop up in
the literature sometimes someone has
like an extra muscle somewhere
in terms of strategies you could try the
two to one method you can try the ankle
weight single leg reverse hyper method
and you can try the single leg day
method where you would perform like a
bilateral day
like say squats deadlifts and hip
thrusts on wednesday
but then on monday and friday you just
do a single leg day
consisting of exercise like single leg
reverse hypers
kickbacks single leg hip thrusts x range
sideline hip abductions and the
three-way band kickback i described
earlier
be sure to hit like if you found this
useful if you have any questions
please ask in the comment section and
make sure you're subscribed to my
channel because i got a lot more to come
thanks for watching now if this video
intrigued you and you would like to
train
under my system using my principles then
i invite you to click on the link below
and subscribe to booty by brett and join
the thousands of other happy members
who are seeing amazing results